Register of the Herbert Hoover subject collection, 1895-2006
Hoover Institution Archives
- SUBJECT FILE, 1900-1964 (Box 326-355)
  - U.S. Congress, government publications annotated by Herbert Hoover. (Box 345)
    - Senate. (Box 350)
      - Armed Services Committee.
        - "Report to the President: Korea,", 1951.
      - Banking and Currency Committee, "Study of Reconstruction Finance Corporation,", 1951.
      - Finance Committee, "Extending Authority to Negotiate Trade Agreements,", 1948.
      - Foreign Relations Committee.
        - "Assignment of Ground Forces of the United States to Duty in the European Area,", 1951.
        - "Legislative History,", 1962.
        - "United Nations Peace Bonds,", 1962.
      - Government Operations Committee.
        - "Army Signal Corps,", 1954.
        - "Congressional Investigations of Communism and Subversive Activities,", 1956.
        - "Progress Report on Science Programs of the Federal Government,", 1958. (Box 352)
        - "Science Program,", 1959.
        - "State Department Information Program,", 1953.
      - Judiciary Committee.
        - "Activities of U.S. Citizens Employed by U.N.,", 1952-1953.
        - "Communist Forgeries,", 1961.
        - "Communist Infiltration in the Nuclear Test Ban Movement,", 1961.
        - "Communist Threat to the U.S. Through the Caribbean,", 1961.
        - "Communist Use and Abuse of U.S. Passports,", 1958.
        - "Cumulative Index to Published Hearings and Reports,", 1957.
        - "Cumulative Index to Published Hearings and Reports - Supplement,", 1962.
        - "Education for Survival in the Struggle Against World Communism,", 1962.
        - "Export of Strategic Materials to the U.S.S.R. and Other Soviet Bloc Countries,", 1961-1962.
        - "Institute of Pacific Relations." (Box 353)
          - 1951.
          - 1952.
          - 1953.
        - "Interlocking Subversion in Government Departments,", 1953-1955.
        - "The New Drive Against the Anti-Communist Program,", 1961.
        - "Problems Raised by the Soviet Oil Offensive,", 1962.
        - "The Pugwash Conferences,", 1961.
        - "Report for the Year 1956,", 1957.
        - "Report for the Year 1957,", 1958.
        - "Safeguard Communications Facilities,", 1961.
        - "Scope of Soviet Activity in the U.S.,", 1956-1957.
        - "Soviet Political Treaties and Violations,", 1955.
        - "Statement by J. Edgar Hoover,", 1957.
        - "Strategy and Tactics of World Communism,", 1954-1956. (Box 354)
        - "Subversive Influences in the Educational Process,", 1953.
        - "Testimony of Former Russian Code Clerk Relating to the Internal Security of the U.S.,", 1955.
      - Labor and Public Welfare Committee.
        - "The Aged and Aging in the U.S.,", 1959-1960.
        - "Federal Programs for the Aged and Aging in the U.S.,", 1959.
        - "Taft-Hartley Act Revisions,", 1953.
      - Military Affairs Committee, "Strategic and Critical Materials,", 1941.
      - Rules and Administration Committee, "Senator from New Mexico,", 1954.
      - Special Committee Investigating the Munitions Industry, 1935.
      - "Summary of Legislation Enacted by the 81st Congress,", 1950.
  - U.S. Food Administration. (Box 355)
  - U.S. Grain Corporation. Statement of accounting, September 1920.
  - United States naval construction and expenditures, 1929-1936.
  - United States Treasury. Annual report, 1935.
  - Wallace, Henry A. New Frontiers, 1934.
  - Water ruling in California.
  - Waterways. Federal Aid for Improvement of Rivers and Canals, 1932.
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman.
  - Wilson, Woodrow.
    - General.
    - Papers deposited at the Library of Congress, index.
    - Televised documentary by Herbert Hoover.
  - Women's International League.
  - Woodrow Wilson Memorial.
  - World War II, Herbert Hoover's position on United States involvement and national defense, 1939-1943.
  - Young Americans for Freedom.
- CARD FILE, n.d. (Box 356-366)
  Handwritten and typescript index cards listing bibliographical and biographical information relating to Herbert Hoover's public career, unsorted.
  - Bibliography of articles about Herbert Hoover, arranged alphabetically by main entry. Typed index cards. (Box 356)
  - Bibliography of articles about Herbert Hoover, arranged alphabetically by title. Typed index cards. (Box 357)
  - Honors conferred on Herbert Hoover, arranged alphabetically. Handwritten, index cards. (Box 358)
    - A - E.
    - F - R. (Box 359)
    - S - Z, and miscellany. (Box 360)
  - Miscellaneous notes on Hoover's life and writings. Unsorted, handwritten index cards. (Box 361)
  - Official positions and honors, arranged by subject and title. Typed index cards. (Box 362)
  - Personnel lists for members of ARA, CRB and contacts made by Hoover during the trip to Europe, Handwritten and typed index cards., 1946-1947. (Box 363)
  - Photographs of Hoover. Unsorted, handwritten index cards. (Box 364)
  - Statements by Hoover, primarily Handwritten and typed index cards., 1930-1941. (Box 365)
  - Statements by Hoover, arranged by subject. Typed index cards. (Box 366)
- INCREMENTS, n.d. (Box 367-385)
  - Increments, of June 1984 and February 1985 (Box 367)
  - Increments of 1985-2011 (Box 368-395)
- MEMORABILIA, 1917-1968
  Gifts, honors, and personal mementos arranged in the following subseries: albums, artifacts and gifts, honorary degrees, distinctions and honors, flags, oversize albums of newspaper clippings, personal effects, portraiture, posters and items in poster format, and presidential campaign memorabilia. Each subseries is arranged either chronologically or alphabetically by subject, as indicated.
  - Albums, arranged chronologically., 1917-1960 (Memorabilia-cabinet Memorabilia cabinet)
    - "To Herbert Hoover from the Staff of the United States Food Administration, August 10, 1917," album of autographs in honor of Hoover's 43rd birthday.
    - "American Relief Administration European Children's Fund--Ceskoslovenska Pece o Dite," inscribed to Hoover in appreciation of relief work, signed by F.G. Masaryk and A.G. Masarykova, Prague, June 1, 1920.
    - "H. H." to Hoover in appreciation of relief work, from the people of Vienna, Austria, June 18, 1921.
    - "Herbertowi Hoover'owi/IV-VII-MCMXXI/ Dzieci rejonu Brzesko-Pinskiego," to Hoover in appreciation of relief work from the children of the Brzesc Pinsk region, Poland, July 4, 1921.
    - "Ksiega autografow przedstawicieli wszystikich stanow Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej Herbertowi Hoover'owi za jego opieke nad dziatwa polska jego hold zlozona," album of autographs representing all strata of the Polish nation, presented as homage to Herbert Hoover for his care of the Polish children, dated 1921, presented in Warsaw, June 1, 1922.
    - "U.S./H.H.," to Hoover in appreciation from the members of the U.S. Food Administration, March 8, 1923.
    - "The School Feeding," collection of 6 letters to Hoover and 113 children's pictures in appreciation of relief work in Germany, 1947.
    - "A Tribute to the Chief," bound volume of letters that accompanied contributions to the Hoover Library in honor of Hoover's 74th birthday, together with a scroll., August 10, 1948
    - "Die deutschen Stadte an Herbert Hoover," decorated album leaves, boxed, from 166 German cities in appreciation of relief work, presented on Hoover's 75th birthday, August 10, 1949.
    - "H. H./75 Years/ 8.10.1949," album of autographs presented to Hoover in appreciation of relief work from the people of Finland, in honor of Hoover's 75th birthday, August 10, 1949.
    - "Die Geschichte von der Hooverspeisung," illustrated story of the Hoover food relief in Germany, presented to Hoover by the people of Stuttgart, 1950.
    - "The Junior Chamber of Commerce Invites the Honorable Herbert Clark Hoover," album of letters inviting Hoover to visit Sacramento, 1957.
    - "The Lou Henry Hoover Room," album of photographs, presented to Hoover in honor of his 86th birthday from the staff of the Hoover Institution, August 10, 1960.
  - Artifacts and gifts, arranged alphabetically., 1915-1968
    - Birthday card, oversize format, signed by Calvin Coolidge et al., In map cabinet., 1928.
    - Buddhist scrolls, in Chinese and Sanskrit
    - California bear, model on wooden base, presented to Hoover by the members of the Electoral College of California, 1929.
    - Cartoon, original, "God Bless Mr. Hoover,", n.d.
    - Cartoon, original, by J.N. Darling, "Home Coming Day in West Branch,"
    - Chinese style painting on silk, n.d.
    - Elephants, models, n.d.
    - Finnish landscape sketch, "Finnish Relief Fund--Herbert Hoover,", 1939.
    - Finnish maps depicting the situation of evacuees, 1940.
    - Finnish miniature flag and base, 1940.
    - Flour sacks, in which grain was shipped to Belgium and Northern France by the Commission for Relief in Belgium; painted, embroidered, and decorated, 1915.
    - Furniture used by Hoover when Secretary of Commerce, Desk and two chairs., 1921-1928.
    - Gavel, commemorating the canalization of the Ohio River, 1929.
    - Gavel, unidentified, n.d.
    - Golden Gate Bridge, etching, signed by the engineer, Joseph B. Strauss, n.d.
    - Inca mask, presented to Hoover by the President of Peru, Augusto B. Leguia, in Lima, December 5, 1928.
    - Ink stand, marble, gift of the Polish-Americans, 1932.
    - Japanese wooden box, contained message sent to Hoover via the Graf Zeppelin from Keigo Kiyoura, president of the Japanese Press Association, 1929.
    - Map, photocopy of plan dated 1587, presented to Hoover during visit to Chateau d'Heverle, University of Louvain, February 22, 1938.
    - Map of property patented by Andrew Hoover, ancestor of Herbert Hoover
    - Maps of Rapidan Camp, oversize format, n.d.
    - Map of Stanford campus, indicating sites of various homes of the Hoover family, 1968.
    - Miscellany.
    - Music, "United States March," decorated and bound sheet music, presented to Hoover by Karoly-Bura, president of the Union of Hungarian Gipsy Musicians, 1930.
    - Pastel sketch, "America the Host," by Alfred Gerstenbrand, presented to Hoover, 1922., 1921
    - Plaque, decorative, crafted by Philip Paval, gift of the American-Scandinavian Foundation, 1940.
    - Printing and photographic plates
    - Russian wooden plate and cloth, signed by S.V. Ivanov
    - Scroll, gift of the Boys Club of San Mateo, 1959.
    - Scroll, remembrance of the Benefit for Destitute Russian Artists, 1922.
    - Sculpture, "Man with a Plow," by R. Solovieva. Cast by V. Taratorin in the Ural mountains, presented in gratitude for Hoover's reorganization of the Kyshtin iron mine in, 1910.
    - Sculpture, untitled, by W. Gontarczyk, Warsaw, inscribed "I remember with gratitude 1914-1920: Don't Forget my Native Country in the Future, 1938."
    - Ship, model of the S.S. President Hoover, n.d.
    - Teapot, silver, n.d.
    - Tiki, gift of the Boys Club of Omaha, Nebraska, 1963.
    - Tray, sterling silver, gift of the ARA Motion Picture Division, n.d.
    - Trays, silver, gift to Hoover from President P. Ortiz Rubio of Mexico, 1931.
    - U.S.S. Maryland, engraved souvenir of trip to Chile, 1928.
    - War Bond pins.
    - White House plan, reproduction of blueprint, n.d., 1807
  - Degrees, honorary, arranged chronologically. Framed photocopies., 1917-1954
    - Harvard University, Massachusetts, honorary LLD, 1917.
    - Oberlin College, Ohio, honorary LLD, 1917.
    - University of Pennsylvania, honorary LLD, 1917.
    - Princeton University, New Jersey, honorary LLD, 1917.
    - Williams College, Massachusetts, honorary LLD, 1917.
    - Yale University, Connecticut, honorary LLD, 1918.
    - University of Liege, Belgium, honorary Doctor of Medicine, 1919.
    - Oxford University, England, honorary Doctor of Civil Law, 1919.
    - Columbia University, New York, honorary LLD, 1920.
    - Dartmouth College, New Hampshire, honorary LLD, 1920.
    - George Washington University, Washington, D.C., honorary LLD, 1920.
    - Johns Hopkins University, Maryland, honorary LLD, 1920.
    - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, New York, honorary Doctor of Engineering, 1920.
    - Rutgers University, New Jersey, honorary LLD, 1920.
    - Swarthmore College, Pennsylvania, honorary LLD, 1920.
    - Tufts College, Massachusetts, honorary Doctor of Science, 1920.
    - Technical University of Prague, Czechoslovakia, honorary Doctor of Technical Sciences, 1921.
    - Christian Albert University, Kiel, Germany, honorary Doctor of Political Science, 1925.
    - University of Missouri, statement by Elmer Ellis, 1925.
    - Georgetown University, Washington, D.C., honorary LLD, 1926.
    - University of Rio de Janeiro, honorary doctorate, 1928.
    - University of Puerto Rico, honorary LLD, 1931.
    - William and Mary College, Virginia, honorary LLD, 1931.
    - Sopron Royal Hungarian Academy of Mining and Forest Engineering, complimentary address, 1931.
    - University of California, Berkeley, honorary LLD, 1935.
    - Colby College, Maine, honorary LLD, 1937.
    - University of Helsinki, honorary doctorate, Photocopy. Original sword and sheath presented with the degree. Top hat worn at the ceremony., 1938.
    - Vienna Technical Institute, honorary Doctor of Technical Science, 1938.
    - Earlham College, Indiana, honorary LLD, 1939.
    - Lincoln Memorial University, Tennessee, Doctor of Humanities, 1939.
    - Stevens Institute of Technology, New Jersey, honorary Doctor of Engineering, 1939.
    - Haverford College, Pennsylvania, honorary LLD, 1941.
    - Clarkson College of Technology, New York, honorary Doctor of Engineering, 1945.
    - New York University, honorary LLD, Two framed photocopies., 1947.
    - University of Washington, St. Louis, honorary degree, tendered, 1949.
    - State University of Iowa, honorary LLD, 1954.
  - Distinctions and honors, arranged chronologically., 1918-1966
    - Ornamental gilded box with embroidered cushion, contained the "Droit de Cite" (honorary citizenship) of Antwerp, Belgium, conferred on Hoover, November 18, 1918.
    - The Washington Award, bronze plaque presented to Hoover for his work as chairman of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, by the Western Society of Engineers, 1919.
    - Certificate of Election, Board of Trustees, Stanford, 1923.
    - Scroll, in honor of Hoover, presented in Guayaquil, Ecuador, 1928.
    - Honorary membership, the New York Marine Society, 1930.
    - Certificate of Election, Board of Trustees, Stanford, 1933.
    - Certificate of appreciation from American engineers to the Hoover-Young Commission relating to the construction of the San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, Framed photocopy., 1936.
    - Scroll, in honor of Hoover, presented by the University of Louvain, Belgium, 1938.
    - Citation awarded Hoover by the American Red Cross for service to the Red Cross War Fund, 1944.
    - Honorary citizenship, Athens, Greece, conferred on Hoover in appreciation of relief work, April 17, 1946.
    - Honorary citizenship, Palo Alto, California, 1949.
    - U.S. Senate concurrent resolution in honor of Hoover's birthday, Framed photocopy., 1949.
    - Resolution in honor of Hoover's 75th birthday, Board of Supervisors, San Francisco, August 8, 1949.
    - Certificate of appreciation from the Salvation Army, Framed photocopy., 1949.
    - Honorary membership, American Boys Club Associates, Framed photocopy., 1953.
    - Gutenberg Award, to Hoover for humanitarian efforts, Framed photocopy., 1954.
    - House of Representatives resolution in honor of Hoover's 80th birthday, Framed photocopy., 1954.
    - U.S. Senate, concurrent resolution in honor of Hoover's 80th birthday, Framed photocopy., 1954.
    - Resolution in honor of Hoover from the Commission on the Organization of the Executive Branch of Government, 1955.
    - Certificate of recognition from the California Republican Assembly, Framed photocopy., 1956.
    - Certificate in honor of Hoover, from the Baronial Order of the Magna Charta, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, Framed photocopy., 1956.
    - Certificate in honor of Hoover, from the organization First Aid for Hungary, Inc., Photocopy., 1956-1957.
    - Resolution in honor of Hoover's 83rd birthday, Board of Supervisors, San Francisco, 1957.
    - Resolution of appreciation, in honor of Hoover, from the Military Order of the World Wars, 1957.
    - Congratulations on Hoover's 84th birthday, from the All Russian Immigrants Association in America, August 10, 1958.
    - Honorary Fellowship, Textile Research Institute, Framed photocopy of certificate., 1960.
    - Medal, Research Institute of America, 1960.
    - Certificate honoring Hoover for 50 years of service as a Stanford Trustee, from the Stanford Board of Trustees, Signed original., 1962.
    - Herbert Hoover Medal for Distinguished Service, named in Hoover's honor and awarded first to him, 1963.
    - Presidential proclamation honoring Hoover's 90th birthday, Photocopy., August 10, 1964.
    - Resolution in honor of Hoover, from the Council of Profit Sharing Industries, 1964.
    - Degree of Uncommon Man, conferred posthumously on Hoover by the Stanford Associates, 1965.
    - Honorary Past Commander-in-Chief, conferred posthumously on Hoover by the Military Order of the World Wars, 1966.
  - Flags, arranged alphabetically., n.d.
    - California Bear Flag and stand, presented to Hoover by the Native Sons of the Golden West
    - Presidential Flag, n.d.
    - Unidentified flag, n.d.
    - United States Flag and stand, gift of Hoover's New York staff in honor of his 86th birthday, August 10, 1960.
    - United States Flag and stand
    - United States Flag, n.d.
  - Newspaper clippings, oversize albums, arranged chronologically. See also clipping file., 1893-1946
    - Palo Alto Times., 1893-1895
    - Daily Palo Alto., 1895
    - various sources. Photocopies., 1898-1920
    - Chicago Daily Tribune. Photocopy., 1928
    - The Minneapolis Journal., 1928
    - various sources., 1946
  - Personal effects, arranged alphabetically., n.d.
    - Addressograph.
    - Ashtrays.
    - Boys Club key ring.
    - Fishing creel.
    - Humidor.
    - Name plate, framed.
    - Name sign, carved wood.
    - Playing cards.
    - Road map of Argentina from South American trip, 1928.
  - Herbert Hoover fishing quote with illuminated letter, undated (Box 385)
  - Political cartoons, referring to the U.S. Food Administration, Original artists' sketches and photocopies., 1917-1918/1949. (Box 385-386)
    - Barclay, McKee, The Baltimore Sun, "The Real Mother Hubbard," Photocopy., 1917.
    - Berrymore, C.K., The Washington Evening Star.
      - "The Canning Season," Photocopy., 1917.
      - "Old Mother Hubbard up to date," Photocopy., 1917.
      - "Sorry, but there'll be no core to waste," Photocopy., June 30, 1917.
      - "U.S., Greatest Corn Crop," Photocopy., 1917.
    - Brinkerhoff, R.M., The New York Evening Mail, "From the Troubles of Herbert C. Hoover," Photocopy., August 21, 1917.
    - Cassel, John, The New York Evening World.
      - "Hands tied," Original sketch., 1917.
      - "Ready," Original sketch., August 11, 1917.
      - "The way to catch the rat," Original sketch., 1917.
    - Darling, J.N. (Ding).
      - "Can't you say something to him, Mr. Hoover?", Photocopy., 1918.
      - "Getting rid of the family pet," Photocopy., 1917.
      - "Oh, Mr. Hoover," Photocopy., 1917.
      - "Tying Hoover's hands," Photocopy., 1917.
    - Donahey, The Cleveland Plain Dealer.
      - "His first square meal since Hoover came," Photocopy., n.d.
      - "Sweetheart, oh, Sweetheart, where'd you plant that potato?", Photocopy., October 7, 1917.
    - Evans, The Baltimore American.
      - "At last I'm out!", Photocopy., 1917.
      - "The first step in food control," Photocopy., June 20, 1917.
    - Fitzpatrick, The St. Louis Post-Dispatch, "The Opposition," Photocopy., 1917.
    - Harding, Nelson, The Brooklyn Eagle, "Next!", Original sketch., June 18, 1917.
    - Hodge, H., The Spokesman Review, Spokane, Washington, "The Slacker," Photocopy., 1917.
    - Kettner, The Western Newspaper Union, "Home Guard," Photocopy., 1917.
    - Knecht, Karl Kae, "Uncle Herbert can tell us a great deal," Photocopies (2)., 1949.
    - Marcus, The New York Times, "Discharging the cabaret," Photocopy., 1917.
    - McCall, Neal, The Portland (Oregon) Telegram, "Stop feeding him or get nothing more from me," Photocopy., July 1917.
    - McCay, Winsor, "Let those give now who never gave before," Original sketch., December 19, 1917.
    - Morgan, The Philadelphia Inquirer, "Slow fuse -- why it isn't even lighted," Original sketch., July 14, 1917.
    - Morris, The New York Evening Mail
      - "Hoover -- That's All," Original sketch., 1917.
      - "Nobody loves us," Photocopy., August 22, 1917.
    - Nap, H., "Ein jeder sollte helfen, dass wir den Krieg gewinnen," Original sketch., 1917.
    - Patrick, W.K., "Hard work holding on to his little pile!", Photocopy., 1917.
    - Plaschke, The Louisville (Kentucky) Times, "Music to his ears," Photocopy., 1917.
    - Rehse, The New York World.
      - "Back to the pen," Photocopy., 1917.
      - "Changing Places," Photocopy., June 22, 1917.
      - "Congress -- Food Control Bill," Photocopy., 1917.
      - "Don't you pity the poor farmer," Photocopy., June 24, 1917.
      - "Overloading the Controller," Photocopy., June 25, 1917.
    - Reynolds, The Portland Oregonian. "World's greatest Santa Claus now on the job in Europe," Photocopy., December 1, 1918.
    - Rogers, W.A., The New York Herald, "Take this Helgoland--or lose the war," Original sketch., June 26, 1917.
    - Tuthill, The St. Louis Star, "Going to tie a can on him," Original sketch., September 18, 1917.
    - Webster, H.T., "A remarkable example of self-control," Photocopy., 1917.
    - "The Congressional Unlimited," The Chicago Tribune, Photocopy., 1917.
    - "A Vision--5 p.m. tomorrow/Somebody's always taking the joy out of life," Original sketch., 1917.
  - Portraiture, arranged approximately chronologically. See also photograph card catalog., 1921-ca. 1960
    - Full-length portrait of Hoover, oil painting, by Ralph Peacock, 1921.
    - Portrait of Hoover, oil painting, by Arthur Cahill, 1925.
    - Bronze bust of Hoover, sculpture by Haig Patigian, 1928.
    - Bust of Hoover, by Fisher Leys, n.d.
    - Portrait of Hoover, engraving, by the U.S. Bureau of Engraving, ca. 1928.
    - Silver cast bas-relief medal of Hoover, by John Ray Sinnock, 1929.
    - Portrait of Hoover, oil painting, by E. Binder
    - Print of sketch of Hoover, by Clarence R. Mattei, 1933.
    - Portrait of Hoover, oil sketch, by John Christen Johansen, 1941.
    - Portrait of Hoover, oil painting, by Howard Chandler Christy, 1944.
    - Pastel portrait of Hoover, by Hugh Moran, 1949.
    - Hoover with group of boys playing checkers, oil painting, by Fred Fredden Goldberg, n.d.
    - Portrait sketch of Hoover with pipe, by Martha Sawyers, n.d.
  - Posters and items in poster format, arranged alphabetically by title., 1928-1962
    - "Herbert Hoover," text by Russell Lee, written for Hoover's 83rd birthday, August 10, 1957.
    - "Herbert Hoover '95: Our Illustrious Stanford Alumnus,", n.d.
    - "The Miracle of America," text by Hoover, n.d.
    - "Ode to Fishing," text by Hoover, n.d.
    - "Pictorial History of Herbert Hoover," from Chicago Daily Tribune, November 3, 1928.
    - "Poverty Will Be Banished,", n.d.
    - "Prayer for Children," text by Francis J. Spellman, signed, 1944.
    - "Something to Think About," text by Hoover, address on the occasion of his 75th birthday celebration, Stanford, 1949.
    - "The State of California, 1850-1950," framed state seal
    - "Thank You, Miss Gray," text by Hoover, n.d.
    - "The Uncommon Man," text by Hoover, 1962.
    - "United Nations International Emergency Children's Fund," text by Maurice Pate